<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>OWASP SAMM</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/</link><description>Recent content on OWASP SAMM</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://owaspsamm.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Towards a well-governed SAMM Suite</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2021/03/23/samm-suite/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2021/03/23/samm-suite/</guid><description>Improving the velocity of OWASP SAMM Some years back, SAMM was a typical old school documentation project. Creation of all the documents was a purely manual and error-prone process. We fought a very complicated manual build procedure of the project PDF which only a few people knew how to deal with. Already fixed errors kept reappearing and it was hard to know who actually had the latest version in their mailbox.</description></item><item><title>OWASP SAMM Roadmap</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2021/02/09/owasp-samm-roadmap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2021/02/09/owasp-samm-roadmap/</guid><description>What happened in 2020? This was a special year but still a lot happened for SAMM. The team worked hard to continue delivering and adding value for our users.
New version, new website, new ways of getting together In 2020 we launched OWASP SAMM v2.0, more than 10 years after OpenSAMM v1.0 was launched on March 25th, 2009 by Pravir Chandra.
Throughout 2020 we developed and released a new website and promoted the launch of SAMM v2.</description></item><item><title>Comparing BSIMM &amp; SAMM</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/10/29/comparing-bsimm-and-samm/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/10/29/comparing-bsimm-and-samm/</guid><description>Building Security In Maturity Model (BSIMM) compared to Software Assurance Maturity Model (SAMM)
A common origin BSIMM (Building Security In Maturity Model) and SAMM (Software Assurance Maturity Model) have similar origins dating back to a common origin back in 2008-2009. I’m frequently asked about what is similar and what is different between the two models, so I wrote up this comparison to help organizations understand which of these two models may be a better fit for their needs.</description></item><item><title>SAMM is doing CI/CD</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/03/31/samm-is-doing-cicd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/03/31/samm-is-doing-cicd/</guid><description>What version 2 brought along A significant change that happened behind the scenes for SAMM 2.0 was the addition of a CI/CD pipeline, the automated version of all the steps we need to deliver SAMM. It has enhanced our productivity, providing standardization and enabling faster iterations. At the core of Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery are speed of delivery, reliability, and visibility. This process encourages frequent updates, allows quick fixes, and ensures a set of checks before deployment.</description></item><item><title>OWASP SAMM version 2 - public release</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/01/31/samm2-release/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/01/31/samm2-release/</guid><description>After three years of preparation, our SAMM project team has delivered version 2 of SAMM! OWASP SAMM (Software Assurance Maturity Model) is the OWASP framework to help organizations assess, formulate, and implement, through our self-assessment model, a strategy for software security they can integrate into their existing Software Development Lifecycle (SDLC).
The new SAMM v2 consists of the following components:
The SAMM Model overview and introduction, explaining the maturity model in detail A Quick-start Guide with different steps to improve your secure software practice An updated SAMM Toolbox to perform SAMM assessments and create SAMM roadmaps A new SAMM Benchmark initiative to compare your maturity and progress with other similar organizations and teams What&amp;rsquo;s changed with SAMM v2?</description></item><item><title>SAMM V2 community release</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/12/20/version2-community-release/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/12/20/version2-community-release/</guid><description>SAMM v2 community launch! After three years of preparation, our SAMM project team has delivered release 2 of SAMM!
First, we&amp;rsquo;re releasing SAMM v2 to the OWASP community and then plan our public release for mid-January 2020. We value your feedback and questions. To contribute, do one of the following, in decreasing order of preference:
add issues to our SAMM Github repository Complete the Google form per issue Start a discussion on our #project-samm Slack channel on OWASP.</description></item><item><title>V2 Toolkit</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/09/03/v2-toolkit/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 13:39:46 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/09/03/v2-toolkit/</guid><description>Call for feedback on new toolkit As part of our work towards OWASP SAMM V2 we&amp;rsquo;ve updated our toolbox. This beta version contains the list of new questions and quality criteria that make up our measurement model. All feedback is welcome. Try it out and get back to us. We&amp;rsquo;d love to hear your thoughts!</description></item><item><title>Open Security Summit 2019</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/07/10/open-security-summit-2019/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 13:07:31 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/07/10/open-security-summit-2019/</guid><description>SAMM track, an overview and commentary of the event The Open Security Summit 2019 focused on the collaboration between Developers and Application Security and was organised with the support of OWASP. The 5-day sprint on SAMMv2 enabled attendees to work and collaborate intensively towards specific Application Security challenges with a focus on actionable outcomes. In addition to specific Maturity Models sessions, a large number of OWASP SAMM Working Sessions took place at the Summit.</description></item><item><title>Version 2 Beta</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/02/02/version2-beta/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 21:49:20 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/02/02/version2-beta/</guid><description>The original model (v1.0) was written by Pravir Chandra and dates back from 2009. Over the last 10 years, it has proven a widely distributed and effective model for improving secure software practices in different types of organisations throughout the world. Translations and supporting tools have been contributed by the community to facilitate adoption and alignment. With version 2.0, we further improve the model to deal with some of its current limitations.</description></item><item><title>About us</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/about/</guid><description>What is OWASP SAMM? SAMM stands for Software Assurance Maturity Model.
Our mission is to provide an effective and measurable way for all types of organizations to analyze and improve their software security posture. We want to raise awareness and educate organizations on how to design, develop, and deploy secure software through our self-assessment model. SAMM supports the complete software lifecycle and is technology and process agnostic. We built SAMM to be evolutive and risk-driven in nature, as there is no single recipe that works for all organizations.</description></item><item><title>Acronyms and Abbreviations</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/acronyms-and-abbreviations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/acronyms-and-abbreviations/</guid><description> AA Architecture Assessment (SAMM Practice) ADFS Active Directory Federation Services ASVS OWASP Application Security Verification Standard AV Anti-Virus BOM Bill of Materials CBT Computer-Based Training CPE Common Platform Enumeration CVE Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures CVSS Common Vulnerability Scoring System CWE Common Weakness Enumeration DAST Dynamic Application Security Testing DDoS Distributed Denial of Service DevOps Integrated Development and Operations/dd DevSecOps Integrated Development, Security, and Operations/dd DM Defect Management (SAMM Practice) DOD Definition of Done DOR Definition of Ready DoS Denial of Service DSL Domain-Specific Language EM Environment Management (SAMM Practice) EG Education and Guidance (SAMM Practice) ESB Enterprise Service Bus GDPR General Data Protection Regulation (European Union law) HSM Hardware Security Module IAM Identity and Access Management IAST Interactive Application Security Testing IDE Integrated Development Environment IM Incident Management (SAMM Practice) IP Internet Protocol ISO International Standards Organization KPI Key Performance Indicator LDAP Lightweight Directory Access Protocol LMS Learning Management System NIST National Institute of Standards and Technology (US Agency) NVD National Vulnerability Database (US) OM Operational Management (SAMM Practice) OS Operating System OWASP Open Web Application Security Project PC Policy and Compliance (SAMM Practice) PCI Payment Card Industry PCI DSS Payment Card Industry Data Security Standard QA Quality Assurance RASP Runtime Application Self-Protection RCA Root Cause Analysis RT Requirements-driven Testing (SAMM Practice) REST REpresentational State Transfer SA Security Architecture (SAMM Practice) SAMM Software Assurance Maturity Model SAST Static Application Security Testing SB Secure Build (SAMM Practice) SD Secure Deployment (SAMM Practice) SDK Software Development Kit SDLC Software Development Life Cycle SIEM Security Information and Event Management SIP Session Initiation Protocol SLA Service Level Agreement SM Strategy and Metrics (SAMM Practice) SMART Specific, Measurable, Actionable, Relevant, and Time-bound SME Subject Matter Expert SOAP Simple Object Access Protocol SP Special Publication (NIST Document) SR Security Requirements (SAMM Practice) SSCE Secure Software Center of Excellence SSO Single Sign-On ST Security Testing (SAMM Practice) STRIDE Spoofing, Tampering, Repudiation, Information disclosure, Denial of service, and Elevation of privilege SWIFT Society for Worldwide Interbank Financial Telecommunication TA Threat Assessment (SAMM Practice) TLS Transport Layer Security TPM Trusted Platform Module UAT User Acceptance Test VA Vulnerability Analysis VCS Version Control System WAF Web Application Firewall ZAP OWASP Zed Attack Proxy</description></item><item><title>Application Risk Profile</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/threat-assessment/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/threat-assessment/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Architecture Assessment</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/architecture-assessment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/architecture-assessment/</guid><description>The Architecture Assessment (AA) practice ensures that the application and infrastructure architecture adequately meets all relevant security and compliance requirements, and sufficiently mitigates identified security threats. The first stream focuses on verifying that the security and compliance requirements identified in the Policy &amp;amp; Compliance and Security Requirements practices are met, first in an ad-hoc manner, then more systematically for each interface in the system. The second stream reviews the architecture, first for mitigations against typical threats, then against the specific threats identified in the Threat Assessment practice.</description></item><item><title>Architecture Design</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-architecture/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-architecture/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Architecture Mitigation</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/architecture-assessment/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/architecture-assessment/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Architecture Validation</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/architecture-assessment/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/architecture-assessment/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Benchmarking</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/benchmarking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/benchmarking/</guid><description>SAMM Benchmarking Goals OWASP SAMM (Software Assurance Maturity Model) Benchmarking is a sub-project within OWASP SAMM to facilitate information and data collaboration between organizations with the goal to help answer the critical questions &amp;ldquo;How am I doing?&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;What might be working for other similar organizations&amp;rdquo;.
The goal of this project is to collect the most comprehensive dataset related to organizational maturity of application or software security programs. Allowing OWASP SAMM to enable comparative analysis for the SAMM practioners and other future research as well.</description></item><item><title>Build Process</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-build/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-build/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Compliance Management</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/policy-and-compliance/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/policy-and-compliance/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Configuration Hardening</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/environment-management/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/environment-management/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/contact/</guid><description>We are here to help you Are you curious about something? Do you want to join as a sponsor? Or maybe host a SAMM training? Please feel free to contact us.</description></item><item><title>Contributing to SAMM</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/contributing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/contributing/</guid><description>Interested in contributing to SAMM? Here&amp;rsquo;s how you can do it!
Link icons indicate links to pages on our website where you can find the information.
Testimonials
Benchmarking How am I doing? What works for similar organizations? Donate SAMM data sets!
Visit our benchmarking page.
GitHub issues
Read more about how we use GitHub for our content and how you can contribute.
Translations</description></item><item><title>Control Verification</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/requirements-driven-testing/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/requirements-driven-testing/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Create and Promote</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/strategy-and-metrics/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/strategy-and-metrics/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Data Protection</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/operational-management/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/operational-management/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Deep Understanding</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/security-testing/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/security-testing/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Defect Management</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/defect-management/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/defect-management/</guid><description>The Defect Management (DM) practice focuses on collecting, recording, and analyzing software security defects and enriching them with information to drive metrics-based decisions.
The practice’s first stream deals with the process of handling and managing defects to ensure released software has a given assurance level. The second stream focuses on enriching the information about the defects and deriving metrics to guide decisions about the security of individual projects and of the security assurance program as a whole.</description></item><item><title>Defect Tracking</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/defect-management/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/defect-management/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Deployment Process</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-deployment/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-deployment/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Design</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/</guid><description>Design concerns the processes and activities related to how an organization defines goals and creates software within development projects. In general, this will include requirements gathering, high-level architecture specification and detailed design.</description></item><item><title>Education &amp; Guidance</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/education-and-guidance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/education-and-guidance/</guid><description>The Education &amp;amp; Guidance (EG) practice focuses on arming personnel involved in the software lifecycle with knowledge and resources to design, develop, and deploy secure software. With improved access to information, project teams can proactively identify and mitigate the specific security risks that apply to their organization.
One major theme for improvement across the Objectives is providing training for employees and increasing their security awareness, either through instructor-led sessions or computer-based modules.</description></item><item><title>Environment Management</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/environment-management/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/environment-management/</guid><description>The organization&amp;rsquo;s work on application security doesn&amp;rsquo;t end once the application becomes operational. New security features and patches are regularly released for the various elements of the technology stack you&amp;rsquo;re using, until they become obsolete or are no longer supported.
Most of the technologies in any application stack are not secure by default. This is frequently intentional, to enhance backwards compatibility or ease of setup. For this reason, ensuring the secure operation of the organization&amp;rsquo;s technology stack requires the consistent application of secure baseline configurations to all components.</description></item><item><title>Events and trainings</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/events/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/events/</guid><description>OWASP SAMM on tour OWASP SAMM: Status and Roadmap February 11th
Presentation by John Ellingsworth
Registration Secure your SDLC using OWASP SAMM - ASAP! March 9th
Training by John Ellingsworth
Join From our archive DevOps Assurance with OWASP SAMMv2 ADDO19
Watch video OWASP SAMM - a dynamic software security journey Global AppSec Amsterdam
Watch video Interested in hosting SAMM?</description></item><item><title>FAQ</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/faq/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/faq/</guid><description>This document is work in progress. It grows with your questions and your feedback. You can always reach out through our contact form or our Slack channel.
Do I need a 1 out of 1 rating for maturity level 1 before working on level 2? It is not strictly required to get a 1 out 1 rating on maturity level 1 to start working on maturity level 2. There might be activities of maturity level 1 that are not relevant for you which you can bypass, moving to maturity level 2 activities.</description></item><item><title>Governance</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/</guid><description>Governance focuses on the processes and activities related to how an organization manages overall software development activities. More specifically, this includes concerns that impact cross-functional groups involved in development, as well as business processes established at the organization level.</description></item><item><title>Implementation</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/</guid><description>Implementation is focused on the processes and activities related to how an organization builds and deploys software components and its related defects.
Activities within the Implementation function have the most impact on the daily life of developers. The joint goal is to ship reliably working software with minimum defects.</description></item><item><title>Incident Detection</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/incident-management/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/incident-management/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Incident Management</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/incident-management/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/incident-management/</guid><description>Once your organization has applications in operation, you&amp;rsquo;re likely to face security incidents. In this model, we define a security incident as a breach, or the threat of an imminent breach, of at least one asset&amp;rsquo;s security goals, whether due to malicious or negligent behavior. Examples of security incidents might include: a successful Denial of Service (DoS) attack against a cloud application, an application user accessing private data of another by abusing a security vulnerability, or an attacker modifying application source code.</description></item><item><title>Incident Response</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/incident-management/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/incident-management/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Mapping SAMM 1.5 to 2.0</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/mapping-versions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/mapping-versions/</guid><description>Overview For those organizations using 1.0 or 1.5 versions of SAMM it&amp;rsquo;s important to take the time to understand how the framework has evolved. Organizations that implemented security initiatives and are looking for SAMM scores to validate effectiveness will need to take these changes into consideration since in most cases expectations for maturity level 3 have been significantly increased in favor of automation and better alignment with development teams.</description></item><item><title>Measure and Improve</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/strategy-and-metrics/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/strategy-and-metrics/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Metrics and Feedback</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/defect-management/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/defect-management/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Misuse/Abuse Testing</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/requirements-driven-testing/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/requirements-driven-testing/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Model diagram</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/diagram/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/diagram/</guid><description>mermaid.initialize({startOnLoad:true}); classDiagram class Model { version: float executiveSummary: string license: string } class BusinessFunction { name: string description: string color: string logoURL: string order: integer } class SecurityPractice { name: string asignee: string shortDescription: string longDescription: string color: string progress: integer order: integer } class ActivityStream { letter: string name: string description: string } class PracticeLevel { description: string } class MaturityLevel { number: integer description: string } class Activity { name: string description: string objective: string notes: string guidance: integer references: Activity } class QualityIndicator { text: string } class CoverageIndicator { text: string value: integer } class CoverageIndicatorSet { name: string } Model &#34;</description></item><item><title>Operational Management</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/operational-management/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/operational-management/</guid><description>The Operational Management (OM) practice focuses on activities to ensure security is maintained throughout operational support functions. Although these functions are not performed directly by an application, the overall security of the application and its data depends on their proper performance. Deploying an application on an unsupported operating system with unpatched vulnerabilities, or failing to store backup media securely, can make the protections built into that application irrelevant.
The functions covered by this practice include, but are not limited to: system provisioning, administration, and decommissioning; database provisioning and administration; and data backup, restore, and archival.</description></item><item><title>Operations</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/</guid><description>The Operations Business Function encompasses those activities necessary to ensure confidentiality, integrity, and availability are maintained throughout the operational lifetime of an application and its associated data. Increased maturity with regard to this Business Function provides greater assurance that the organization is resilient in the face of operational disruptions, and responsive to changes in the operational landscape.</description></item><item><title>Organization and Culture</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/education-and-guidance/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/education-and-guidance/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Patching and Updating</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/environment-management/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/environment-management/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Policy &amp; Compliance</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/policy-and-compliance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/policy-and-compliance/</guid><description>The Policy &amp;amp; Compliance (PC) practice focuses on understanding and meeting external legal and regulatory requirements while driving internal security standards to ensure compliance in a way that’s aligned with the business purpose of the organization.
A driving theme for improvement within this practice is describing organization’s standards and 3rd party obligations as application requirements, enabling efficient and automated audits that may be leveraged within the SDLC and continuously demonstrate that all expectations are met.</description></item><item><title>Policy &amp; Standards</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/policy-and-compliance/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/policy-and-compliance/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Quick start guide for version 2.0</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/guidance/quick-start-guide/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/guidance/quick-start-guide/</guid><description>About OWASP SAMM OWASP SAMM (Software Assurance Maturity Model) is the OWASP framework to help organizations assess, formulate, and implement a strategy for software security, that can be integrated into their existing Software Development Lifecycle (SDLC). OWASP SAMM is fit for most contexts, whether your organization is mainly developing, outsourcing, or acquiring software, or whether you are using a waterfall, an agile or devops method, the same model can be applied.</description></item><item><title>Release notes OWASP SAMM version 2</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/release-notes-v2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/release-notes-v2/</guid><description>Key changes in OWASP SAMM v2 The new SAMM version 2 consists of the following components:
the SAMM Model overview and introduction, explaining the maturity model in detail a Quick-start Guide with different steps to improve your secure software practice an updated SAMM Toolbox to perform SAMM assessments and create SAMM roadmaps a new SAMM Benchmark initiative to compare your maturity and progress with other similar organizations and teams The original model OpenSAMM 1.</description></item><item><title>Requirements-driven Testing</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/requirements-driven-testing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/requirements-driven-testing/</guid><description>The goal of the Requirements-driven Testing (RT) practice is to ensure that the implemented security controls operate as expected and satisfy the project&amp;rsquo;s stated security requirements. It does so by incrementally building a set of security test and regression cases and executing them regularly.
A key aspect of this practice is its attention to both positive and negative testing. The former verifies that the application&amp;rsquo;s security controls satisfy stated security requirements and validates their correct functioning.</description></item><item><title>SAMM Agile Guidance</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/guidance/agile/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/guidance/agile/</guid><description>Overview This document explains how SAMM security practices work for Agile to attain the continuous building in of sufficient security during software development. It&amp;rsquo;s structured in the form of best practices and pitfalls.
Why SAMM Agile guidance The Software Assurance Maturity Model (SAMM) is an OWASP flagship project on how to set up and grow a secure development process. It is agnostic of the development approach, which is why Agile is not explicitly covered.</description></item><item><title>SAMM Assessment</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/assessment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/assessment/</guid><description>SAMM Assessment The SAMM v2 assessment Toolbox has been improved to measure the quality of you own software assurance maturity performance. Our Toolbox allows you to review your security activities against the defined quality criteria and calculate your maturity score.
Self-assessment Your first step towards improvement, is to measure where you are now.
Make sure you first read our getting started guide, then you can start with assessing your current software assurance posture.</description></item><item><title>Scalable Baseline</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/security-testing/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/security-testing/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Secret Management</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-deployment/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-deployment/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Secure Build</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-build/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-build/</guid><description>The Secure Build (SB) practice emphasises the importance of building software in a standardised, repeatable manner, and of doing so using secure components, including 3rd party software dependencies.
The first stream focuses on removing any subjectivity from the build process by striving for full automation. An automated build pipeline can include additional automated security checks such as SAST and DAST to gain further assurance and flag security regressions early by failing the build, for example.</description></item><item><title>Secure Deployment</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-deployment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-deployment/</guid><description>One of the final stages in delivering secure software is ensuring the security and integrity of developed applications are not compromised during deployment. The Secure Deployment (SD) practice focuses on this. To this end, the practice’s first stream focuses on removing manual error by automating the deployment process as much as possible, and making its success contingent upon the outcomes of integrated security verification checks. It also fosters Separation of Duties by making adequately trained, non-developers responsible for deployment.</description></item><item><title>Security Architecture</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-architecture/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-architecture/</guid><description>The Security Architecture (SA) practice focuses on the security linked to components and technology you deal with during the architectural design of your software. Secure Architecture Design looks at the selection and composition of components that form the foundation of your solution, focusing on its security properties. Technology management looks at the security of supporting technologies used during development, deployment and operations, such as development stacks and tooling, deployment tooling, and operating systems and tooling.</description></item><item><title>Security Requirements</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-requirements/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-requirements/</guid><description>The Security Requirements (SR) practice focuses on security requirements that are important in the context of secure software. A first type deals with typical software-related requirements, to specify objectives and expectations to protect the service and data at the core of the application. A second type deals with requirements relative to supplier organizations that are part of the development context of the application, in particular for outsourced development. It is important to streamline the expectations in terms of secure development because outsourced development can have significant impact on the security of the application.</description></item><item><title>Security Testing</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/security-testing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/security-testing/</guid><description>The Security Testing (ST) practice leverages the fact that, while automated security testing is fast and scales well to numerous applications, in-depth testing based on good knowledge of an application and its business logic is often only possible via slower, manual expert security testing. Each stream therefore has one approach at its core.
The first stream focuses on establishing a common security baseline to automatically detect so-called &amp;ldquo;low hanging fruit&amp;rdquo;. Progressively customize the automated tests for each application and increase their frequency of execution to detect more bugs and regressions earlier, as close as possible to their inception.</description></item><item><title>Software Dependencies</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-build/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/implementation/secure-build/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Software Requirements</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-requirements/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-requirements/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Sponsors</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/sponsors/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/sponsors/</guid><description>By sponsoring SAMM, you support a Flagship OWASP project. The OWASP Flagship designation is given to projects that have demonstrated strategic value to OWASP and application security as a whole.
Don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to contact us.
Proceeds All proceeds from the sponsorship support the mission of the OWASP Foundation and the further development of SAMM, funding
marketing &amp;amp; PR support technical editing &amp;amp; UX support website development and hosting SAMM participation in the Open Security Summit core team summits tooling for the SAMM Benchmark project Sponsorship levels Sponsorship level Supporter Ambassador Leader Price (in USD) 1000 2500 5000 Sponsorship benefits Website benefit: listing on Supporter Ambassador Leader owaspsamm.</description></item><item><title>Strategy &amp; Metrics</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/strategy-and-metrics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/strategy-and-metrics/</guid><description>Software assurance entails many different activities and concerns. Without an overall plan, you might be spending a lot of effort to build in security, while in fact your efforts may be unaligned, disproportional or even counterproductive. The goal of the Strategy &amp;amp; Metrics (SM) practice is to build an efficient and effective plan for realizing your software security objectives within your organization.
A software security program, that selects and prioritizes activities of the rest of the model, serves as the foundation for your efforts.</description></item><item><title>Supplier Security</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-requirements/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-requirements/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>System Decomissioning / Legacy Management</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/operational-management/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/operations/operational-management/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Technology Management</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-architecture/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/security-architecture/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Model</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/</guid><description>SAMM model overview Governance Design Implementation Verification Operations Strategy and Metrics Threat Assessment Secure Build Architecture Assessment Incident Management Policy and Compliance Security Requirements Secure Deployment Requirements-driven Testing Environment Management Education and Guidance Security Architecture Defect Management Security Testing Operational Management Introduction The mission of OWASP Software Assurance Maturity Model (SAMM) is to be the prime maturity model for software assurance that provides an effective and measurable way for all types of organizations to analyze and improve their software security posture.</description></item><item><title>Threat Assessment</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/threat-assessment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/threat-assessment/</guid><description>The Threat Assessment (TA) practice focuses on identifying and understanding of project-level risks based on the functionality of the software being developed and characteristics of the runtime environment. From details about threats and likely attacks against each project, the organization as a whole operates more effectively through better decisions about prioritization of initiatives for security. Additionally, decisions for risk acceptance are more informed, therefore better aligned to the business.
By starting with simple threat models and building application risk profiles, an organization improves over time.</description></item><item><title>Threat Modeling</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/threat-assessment/stream-b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/design/threat-assessment/stream-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Training and Awareness</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/education-and-guidance/stream-a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/governance/education-and-guidance/stream-a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/agile-guidance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/agile-guidance/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/content-security-in-federated-media-cloud-workflows/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/content-security-in-federated-media-cloud-workflows/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/contributing-to-samm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/contributing-to-samm/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/integrating-samm-into-consulting-assessments/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/integrating-samm-into-consulting-assessments/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/lean-security-in-devsecops/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/lean-security-in-devsecops/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/owasp-categories-for-security-champions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/owasp-categories-for-security-champions/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/samm-benchmark/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/samm-benchmark/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/samm-dashboard/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/samm-dashboard/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/samm-to-kickstart-the-tssdlc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/samm-to-kickstart-the-tssdlc/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/samm-tools-of-the-trade/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/samm-tools-of-the-trade/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/samm-update/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/samm-update/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/sins-of-samm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/sins-of-samm/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/user-day-wrap-up/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/2020/user-day-wrap-up/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/from-samm-project-towards-samm-suite/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/from-samm-project-towards-samm-suite/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/organizational-scope-of-an-owasp-samm-assessment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/organizational-scope-of-an-owasp-samm-assessment/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/owasp-samm-to-the-rescue/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/owasp-samm-to-the-rescue/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/implementation-of-samm-in-k12-schools/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/implementation-of-samm-in-k12-schools/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/samm-update/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/samm-update/</guid><description/></item><item><title>User day</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/strategic-usage-of-samm-and-dsomm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/user-day/strategic-usage-of-samm-and-dsomm/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Verification</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/model/verification/</guid><description>Verification focuses on the processes and activities related to how an organization checks and tests artifacts produced throughout software development. This typically includes quality assurance work such as testing, but it can also include other review and evaluation activities.</description></item><item><title>Version 1.5</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/v1-5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/v1-5/</guid><description> While we recommend to use the latest version of SAMM, here are is the version 1.5:
Downloads Core Model How-to Guide Quick Start Guide See also SAMM 1.5 Assessment Toolbox SAMM 1.5 Assessment Toolbox Example SAMM project page - OWASP website</description></item></channel></rss>