<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>SAMM on OWASP SAMM</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/tags/samm/</link><description>Recent content in SAMM on OWASP SAMM</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://owaspsamm.org/tags/samm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Towards a well-governed SAMM Suite</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2021/03/23/samm-suite/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2021/03/23/samm-suite/</guid><description>Improving the velocity of OWASP SAMM Some years back, SAMM was a typical old school documentation project. Creation of all the documents was a purely manual and error-prone process. We fought a very complicated manual build procedure of the project PDF which only a few people knew how to deal with. Already fixed errors kept reappearing and it was hard to know who actually had the latest version in their mailbox.</description></item><item><title>OWASP SAMM Roadmap</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2021/02/09/owasp-samm-roadmap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2021/02/09/owasp-samm-roadmap/</guid><description>What happened in 2020? This was a special year but still a lot happened for SAMM. The team worked hard to continue delivering and adding value for our users.
New version, new website, new ways of getting together In 2020 we launched OWASP SAMM v2.0, more than 10 years after OpenSAMM v1.0 was launched on March 25th, 2009 by Pravir Chandra.
Throughout 2020 we developed and released a new website and promoted the launch of SAMM v2.</description></item><item><title>Comparing BSIMM &amp; SAMM</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/10/29/comparing-bsimm-and-samm/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/10/29/comparing-bsimm-and-samm/</guid><description>Building Security In Maturity Model (BSIMM) compared to Software Assurance Maturity Model (SAMM)
A common origin BSIMM (Building Security In Maturity Model) and SAMM (Software Assurance Maturity Model) have similar origins dating back to a common origin back in 2008-2009. I’m frequently asked about what is similar and what is different between the two models, so I wrote up this comparison to help organizations understand which of these two models may be a better fit for their needs.</description></item></channel></rss>