<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Design on OWASP SAMM</title>
    <link>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/design/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Design on OWASP SAMM</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Threat Assessment</title>
      <link>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/design/d-threat-assessment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/design/d-threat-assessment/</guid>
      <description>Short Description Threat Assessment focuses on identifying threats in applications.
Long Description The Threat Assessment (TA) practice focuses on accurately identifying and understanding potential attacks upon an organisation&amp;rsquo;s software to better understand the risks and facilitate risk management. Indeed, software assurance is all about identifying risks in applications and treating them accordingly.
Risks to an application can be relative to the business of the application (think about business logic attacks) or to the technical setup of the application.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Security Requirements</title>
      <link>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/design/d-security-requirements/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/design/d-security-requirements/</guid>
      <description>Short Description This practice focuses on defining appropriate security requirements for your software and your software suppliers.
Long Description This practice focuses on security requirements that are important in the context of secure software. A first type deals with typical software-related requirements, to specify objectives and expectations to protect the service and data at the core of the application. A second type deals with requirements that are relative to supplier organisations that are part of the development context of the application, in particular for outsourced development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Security Architecture</title>
      <link>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/design/d-security-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/design/d-security-architecture/</guid>
      <description>Short Description The security architecture practice focuses on managing architectural risks for the software solution.
Long Description This practice focuses on the security linked to components and technology you deal with during the design of the architecture of your software. Secure Architecture Design looks at the selection and composition of components that form the foundation of your solution, focusing on its security properties. Technology management looks at the security of supporting technologies used during development, deployment and operations, such as development stacks and tooling, deployment tooling, and operating systems and tooling.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>