<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Operations on OWASP SAMM</title>
    <link>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/operations/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Operations on OWASP SAMM</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/operations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Incident Management</title>
      <link>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/operations/o-incident-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/operations/o-incident-management/</guid>
      <description>Short Description The Incident Management practice addresses activities carried out improve the organization&amp;rsquo;s detection of, and response to, security incidents.
Long Description Once your organization has applications in operation, you&amp;rsquo;re likely to face security incidents. In this model, we define a security incident as a breach, or the threat of an imminent breach, of at least one asset&amp;rsquo;s security goals, whether due to malicious or negligent behavior. Examples of security incidents might include: - a successful Denial of Service (DoS) attack against a cloud application; - an application user accessing private data of another, by abusing a security vulnerability; or - an attacker modifying application source code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environment Management</title>
      <link>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/operations/o-environment-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/operations/o-environment-management/</guid>
      <description>Short Description The Environment Management practice describes proactive activities carried out to improve and maintain the security of the environments in which the organization&amp;rsquo;s applications operate.
Long Description The organization&amp;rsquo;s work on application security doesn&amp;rsquo;t end once the application becomes operational. New security features and patches are regularly released for the various elements of the technology stack you&amp;rsquo;re using, until they become obsolete or are no longer supported.
Most of the technologies in any application stack are not secure by default.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operational Management</title>
      <link>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/operations/o-operational-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owaspsamm.org/head/core/operations/o-operational-management/</guid>
      <description>Short Description The Operational Management practice focuses on operational support activities required to maintain security throughout the product lifecycle.
Long Description The Operational Management practice focuses on activities to ensure security is maintained throughout operational support functions. Although these functions are not performed directly by an application, the overall security of the application and its data depends on their proper performance. Deploying an application on an unsupported operating system with unpatched vulnerabilities, or failing to store backup media securely, can make the protections built into that application irrelevant.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>