<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on OWASP SAMM</title>
    <link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on OWASP SAMM</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 13:39:46 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://owaspsamm.org/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>V2 Toolkit</title>
      <link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/09/03/v2-toolkit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 13:39:46 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/09/03/v2-toolkit/</guid>
      <description>Call for feedback on new toolkit As part of our work towards OWASP SAMM V2 we&amp;rsquo;ve updated our toolbox. This beta version contains the list of new questions and quality criteria that make up our measurement model. All feedback is welcome. Try it out and get back to us. We&amp;rsquo;d love to hear your thoughts!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Security Summit 2019</title>
      <link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/07/10/open-security-summit-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 13:07:31 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/07/10/open-security-summit-2019/</guid>
      <description>SAMM track, an overview and commentary of the event The Open Security Summit 2019 focused on the collaboration between Developers and Application Security and was organised with the support of OWASP. The 5-day sprint on SAMMv2 enabled attendees to work and collaborate intensively towards specific Application Security challenges with a focus on actionable outcomes. In addition to specific Maturity Models sessions, a large number of OWASP SAMM Working Sessions took place at the Summit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 2 Beta</title>
      <link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/02/02/version2-beta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 21:49:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/02/02/version2-beta/</guid>
      <description>The original model (v1.0) was written by Pravir Chandra and dates back from 2009. Over the last 10 years, it has proven a widely distributed and effective model for improving secure software practices in different types of organisations throughout the world. Translations and supporting tools have been contributed by the community to facilitate adoption and alignment. With version 2.0, we further improve the model to deal with some of its current limitations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generic blog post</title>
      <link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2018/09/17/generic-blog-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2018 13:47:08 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2018/09/17/generic-blog-post/</guid>
      <description>Add at least one more blog post to start with a reasonable number of articles.
  If one examines substructural depatriarchialism, one is faced with a choice: either accept Lacanist obscurity or conclude that expression is a product of communication. The example of Lyotardist narrative which is a central theme of Fellini’s Satyricon emerges again in 8 1&amp;frasl;2. However, the primary theme of Finnis’s[1] essay on Lacanist obscurity is a mythopoetical totality.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>