<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on OWASP SAMM</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blogs on OWASP SAMM</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://owaspsamm.org/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SAMM is doing CI/CD</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/03/31/samm-is-doing-cicd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/03/31/samm-is-doing-cicd/</guid><description>What version 2 brought along A significant change that happened behind the scenes for SAMM 2.0 was the addition of a CI/CD pipeline, the automated version of all the steps we need to deliver SAMM. It has enhanced our productivity, providing standardization and enabling faster iterations. At the core of Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery are speed of delivery, reliability, and visibility. This process encourages frequent updates, allows quick fixes, and ensures a set of checks before deployment.</description></item><item><title>OWASP SAMM version 2 - public release</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/01/31/samm2-release/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2020/01/31/samm2-release/</guid><description>After three years of preparation, our SAMM project team has delivered version 2 of SAMM! OWASP SAMM (Software Assurance Maturity Model) is the OWASP framework to help organizations assess, formulate, and implement, through our self-assessment model, a strategy for software security they can integrate into their existing Software Development Lifecycle (SDLC).
The new SAMM v2 consists of the following components:
The SAMM Model overview and introduction, explaining the maturity model in detail A Quick-start Guide with different steps to improve your secure software practice An updated SAMM Toolbox to perform SAMM assessments and create SAMM roadmaps A new SAMM Benchmark initiative to compare your maturity and progress with other similar organizations and teams What&amp;rsquo;s changed with SAMM v2?</description></item><item><title>SAMM V2 community release</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/12/20/version2-community-release/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/12/20/version2-community-release/</guid><description>SAMM v2 community launch! After three years of preparation, our SAMM project team has delivered release 2 of SAMM!
First, we&amp;rsquo;re releasing SAMM v2 to the OWASP community and then plan our public release for mid-January 2020. We value your feedback and questions. To contribute, do one of the following, in decreasing order of preference:
add issues to our SAMM Github repository Complete the Google form per issue Start a discussion on our #project-samm Slack channel on OWASP.</description></item><item><title>V2 Toolkit</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/09/03/v2-toolkit/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 13:39:46 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/09/03/v2-toolkit/</guid><description>Call for feedback on new toolkit As part of our work towards OWASP SAMM V2 we&amp;rsquo;ve updated our toolbox. This beta version contains the list of new questions and quality criteria that make up our measurement model. All feedback is welcome. Try it out and get back to us. We&amp;rsquo;d love to hear your thoughts!</description></item><item><title>Open Security Summit 2019</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/07/10/open-security-summit-2019/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 13:07:31 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/07/10/open-security-summit-2019/</guid><description>SAMM track, an overview and commentary of the event The Open Security Summit 2019 focused on the collaboration between Developers and Application Security and was organised with the support of OWASP. The 5-day sprint on SAMMv2 enabled attendees to work and collaborate intensively towards specific Application Security challenges with a focus on actionable outcomes. In addition to specific Maturity Models sessions, a large number of OWASP SAMM Working Sessions took place at the Summit.</description></item><item><title>Version 2 Beta</title><link>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/02/02/version2-beta/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 21:49:20 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://owaspsamm.org/blog/2019/02/02/version2-beta/</guid><description>The original model (v1.0) was written by Pravir Chandra and dates back from 2009. Over the last 10 years, it has proven a widely distributed and effective model for improving secure software practices in different types of organisations throughout the world. Translations and supporting tools have been contributed by the community to facilitate adoption and alignment. With version 2.0, we further improve the model to deal with some of its current limitations.</description></item></channel></rss>